# PRANJAL SINGH

CLOUD SOLUTION ENGINEER

+91 9424509772



pranjalsingh1@outlook.com



**BANGALORE** 



I possess a strong and diverse background in designing, implementing, and optimizing cloud-based solutions with over 5 years of experience in the industry, I have developed a deep understanding of cloud computing technologies and best practices.

**SUMMARY** 

# **SKILLS**

- Azure Migrate
- Cost Optimization
- Powershell
- Azure Monitor
- Azure Entra ID (AD)
- · VMware Cloud Health
- SPOT by NetApp
- Virtual Machines
- Azure Site Recovery
- Migrated On-Prem to Azure through ASR.
- · Monitoring and Management
- Azure Storage
- Azure Security: Sentinel, Azure ATP, Information Protection Security Centre
- VM Scale Set
- Pre-sales
- · RFP Architecture and designing

# **CERTIFICATIONS**

- Microsoft certified Azure Administrator (AZ-104)
- Microsoft certified Microsoft 365 Fundamentals (MS-900)
- Microsoft certified Azure Fundamentals (AZ-900)
- IBM Turbonomics (Instana by IBM)
- Technical Sales Turbonomic by IBM (Sales)
- NetApp SPOT Pre-Sales

## **EDUCATION**

#### Gyan Ganga Institute of Technology & Sciences

Bachelor's in Engineering from Information Technology 2015 – 2019

#### Maharishi Vidya Mandir

Senior Secondary (12th) | PCM 2014 - 2015

# Christ Church Boys' Senior Secondary

Secondary (10th) 2012 – 2013

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

### Crayon Software Experts Pvt. Ltd.

Cloud Solution Engineer | Bangalore (K.A.) | June 2022 - Present

- Migrated on-premises infrastructure to Azure using Azure Migrate
- Implemented FinOps best practices for optimizing cloud spending and enhancing financial visibility for stakeholders.
- Cloud Solution Design: Designed and proposed cloud architecture solutions on AWS and Azure.
- Assisted clients in budget planning and forecasting by analyzing consumption data and identifying cost-saving opportunities.
- Analyzed consumption reports to assist customers in reducing costs
- Leveraged FinOps tools like CloudHealth and SPOT by NetApp for automated cost management solutions.
- Focus on cost optimization using Azure Portal, VMware Cloud Health, SPOT by NetApp and IBM Turbonomics
- Managed Azure storage and security including Sentinel, Azure ATP, and Information Protection
- Implemented VM Scale Set

#### Skillup Technologies Pvt. Ltd.

Technical Cloud Specialist | Noida (U.P.) | October 2020 - May 2022

- Migrated VMware workloads to Microsoft Azure
- Configured VMware and Azure Site Recovery based on client requirements
- Focused on workload rightsizing and resource allocation to optimize cloud expenses.
- Provided insights on cost drivers and helped organizations align cloud investments with business outcomes.
- Used technologies such as VMware, Windows Azure, Azure Site Recovery, Virtual Network, Storage, and Azure Image
- Implemented hybrid identity solutions by migrating Windows AD to Azure AD using Azure AD, Windows AD, and AD Connect

#### **Cloud Garage**

Cloud Consultant | Gurgaon (H.R.) | September 2019 – October 2020

- Experience in Cloud Architecture, Automation, Optimization, Storage, Virtualization, troubleshooting, and Designing fault-tolerant Cloud Infrastructure.
- Delivered cost management solutions tailored to client-specific cloud environments.
- Simplify and solve IT infrastructure using the best technology available and optimizing in the most efficient way to meet the set goal.
- Working with customers to deliver their architecture on the azure platform, providing architectural advice, analyzing the requirement, developing specifications, technical product knowledge and technical review.